I don't speak English.
انا لا أتحدث الانجليزية
I start speaking English, learning English, about a year ago.
بدأت تعلم الانجليزية والتحدث بها منذ عام تقريبا
I speak French and I grew up with French, so my English is Franglais.
كبرت وأنا أتحدث الفرنسية لذا فإن انجليزيتي فرنجلي (فرنسية –انجليزية)
I'm born in the Western Congo, in an area around here,
ولدت في غرب الكونغو في منطقة قريبة من هنا
and then went to university in Kisangani.
ثم التحقت بجامعة في كيسانجاني
And after I finished, I went to this area, the Ituri Forest.
بعد انهائي للمرحلة الجامعية عدت الى هذه المنطقة غابات ايتوري
But what I've been doing --
لكن ماذا كنت أعمل ؟
when I was about 14, I grew in my uncle's house.
عندما كنت في 14من عمري كبرت في منزل عمي
And my father was a soldier,
والدي كان جنديا
and my uncle was a fisherman and also a poacher.
والدي كان جنديا اما عمي فلقد كان صياد سمك وصائد حيوانات
What I've been doing from 14 to 17 was,
من الـ14 الى الـ17 من عمري كنت
I was assisting them collecting ivory tusk, meat
كنت أساعدهم في جمع الأنياب العاجية, اللحم
and whatever they were killing, poaching, hunting in the forest,
ومهما كانوا يقتلون,يسرقون ويصطادون من الغابة
bring it in the main city to get access to the market.
يحضرونه الى المدينة ليبيعوه في السوق
But finally, I got myself involved.
لكن أخيرا جعلت نفسي متورطا
Around 17 to 20 years, I became, myself, a poacher.
حوالي الـ17 الى الـ20 عاما أصبحت صيادا
And I wanted to do it, because -- I believed -- to continue my studies.
أردت أن أعمل لأكمل دراستي
I wanted to go to university, but my father was poor, my uncle even.
أردت الذهاب الى الجامعة لكن والدي كان فقيرا كذلك عمي
So, I did it.
لذلك لجأت للعمل كصياد
And for three to four years, I went to university.
ذهبت الى الجامعة لحوالي ثلاث الى أربع سنوات.
For three times, I applied to biomedical science, to be a doctor.
قدمت ثلاث مرات في كلية العلوم الطبية لأصبح طبيبا
I didn't succeed.
لكنني لم أنجح
I was having my inscriptions, my admission to biology.
كان لدي ميول لعلم الاحياء
And I said, "No way, I'm not doing it.
قلت مستحيل لن أقوم بهذا
My family's poor, my area don't have better health care.
عائلتي فقيرة ومنطقتي لاتمتلك رعاية طبية جيدة
I want to be a doctor to serve them."
. كنت أود أن أصبح طبيبا لأخدمهم
Three times, that means three years, and I start getting old.
ثلاث مرات , هذا يعني ثلاث سنوات وانا أكبر
I say, "Oh, no, I continue."
قلت لا سأستمر
So, I did tropical ecology and plant botany.
لذا درست علم البيئة الاستوائي وعلم النبات .
When I finished, I went to the Ituri Forest for my internship.
فور انتهائي من الدراسة عدت الى غابات ايتوري لانهي فترة التخصص
It's where I really getting passion with what I'm doing
حيث أجد الشغف مترافقا مع ما أعمل
right up to now -- I'm standing in front of you --
.الان أنا أقف أمامكم
doing botany and wildlife conservation.
أدرس علم النبات مع حماية الحياة البرية
That time the Ituri Forest was created as a forest reserve
في ذلك الوقت غابات ايتوري وُجدت كغابات لحفظ
with some animals and also plants.
بعض أنواع الحيوانات والنباتات
And the training center there was built
بني مركز التدريب هناك
around the scientific Congolese staff
بالقرب من مركز الموظفين الكونغوليين العلميين
and some American scientists also.
وبعض المراكز العلمية الأميركية
So, the Okapi Faunal Reserve protects number --
لذا كانت محمية أوكابي الحيوانية تحتفظ بعدد محمي –
I think that is the largest number of elephants
أعتقد بأن العدد الاكبر من الفيلة
we have right now in protected areas in Congo.
موجود حاليا في منطقة الكونغو المحية
It has also chimpanzees.
يوجد في المحمية أيضا قردة الشمبانزي .
And it has been named Okapi Faunal Reserve
سُميت محمية أوكابي بهذا الاسم
because of this beautiful creature.
نسبة لزرافات الأوكابي ذاك المخلوق الجميل
That is a forest giraffe.
.تلك غابة الزرافات
I think you guys know it quite well.
أعتقد بأنكم تعرفونها جيدا
Here we have savanna giraffes,
هنا لدينا سهول عشبية للزرافات
but through evolution we have this forest giraffe
لكن خلال التطورات لايوجد سوى هذه الغابة
that lives only in Congo.
الموجودة فقط في الكونغو
It has also some beautiful primates.
تحوي أيضا بعض القرود الجميلة
Thirteen species -- highest diversity we can find in one single area in Africa.
.13 نوع – أكبر تنوع بيلوجي قد نجده في منطقة واحدة في افريقيا
And it has the Ituri Forest itself --
هي غابات ايتوري—
about 1,300 species of plants, so far known.
مايقارب ال1300 نوع من النباتات تم اكتشافه الى حد الان
I joined the Wildlife Conservation Society, working there, in 1995,
انضممت لمنظمة حماية الحياة البرية هنا في عام 1995
but I started working with them as a student in 1991.
لكنني بدأت العمل معهم كطالب في عام 1991
I was appointed as a teaching assistant at my university
عُينت كمدرس مساعد في جامعتي
because I accomplished with honor.
بعد تخرجي بمرتبة الشرف
But I didn't like the way -- the instruction I got was very poor.
لكن مستوى التعليم الذي كنت اتلقاه لم يرق لي لضعفه
And I wanted to be formed to a training center and a research center.
اتجهت للعمل بمركز التدريب ومركز البحوث
With the end of the dictatorship regime of Mobutu Sese Seko,
في نهاية النظام الدكتاتوري لموبوتو سيسي سيكو
that most of you know, life became very, very difficult.
- أغلبكم يعرفه- باتت الحياة صعبة جدا
And the work we have been doing
والعمل الذي كنا ننجزه
was completely difficult to do and to achieve it.
بات من الصعب انجازه وانهائه
When Kabila started his movement to liberate Congo,
عندما بدأ كابيلا بحركات التحرر في الكونغو
so Mobutu soldiers started moving and retreated.
بدأت جيوش موبوتو بالتحرك
So they started fleeing from the east to the west.
والانسحاب والهرب من الشرق الى الغرب
And the Okapi Faunal Reserve is there,
محمية أوكابي الحيوانية كانت هنا
so there was a road from Goma, somewhere here,
وهنا كان طريق من غوما في مكان ما هنا
and coming like this.
ياتي بهذا الشكل
So they might go through, pass through the Okapi Faunal Reserve.
لذا قد يمر به . يمر من خلال محمية أوكابي الحيوانية
Congo has five of the world's richest sites of protected area,
الكونغو تحوي خمس أغنى المناطق المحمية في العالم
and the Okapi Faunal Reserve is one of them.
ومحمية أوكابي الحيوانية واحدة منهم
So soldier was fleeing in the Okapi Faunal Reserve.
كان الجنود يفرون عن طريق محمية أوكابي الحيوانية
On their way, they looted everything.
وخلال طريقهم نهبوا كل شيء
Torture, wars -- oh, my God, you can't believe.
ارهاب – حرب – يا الهي لاتستيطعون التخيل
Every person was looking his way -- where to go, we don't know.
كل انسان كان يحاول البحث عن مكان يلجأ اليه . لم نكن نعلم
And it was for us, the young, the first time really
كل هذا كان جديدا علينا . انها المرة الاولى
we hear the language of war, of guns.
التي نشهد فيها لغة الحرب والمسدسات
And even people who faced the rebellion of 1963,
حتى أولئك الاشخاص الذين عاصروا التمرد في عام 1963
after our independence, they didn't believe what was happening.
بعد الاستقلال لم يصدقوا ماحدث
They were killing people. They were doing whatever they want
كانوا يقتلون الناس ,كانوا يفعلون مايريدون
because they have power.
فقط لأنهم يملكون القوة .
Who have been doing that?
من كان يفعل ذلك؟
Young children. Child soldiers.
أطفال صغار أطفال جنود
You can't ask him how old he is because he has guns.
لاتستطيع أن تسأله عن عمره لأنه يحمل مسدس
But I was from the west, working in the east.
لكن أنا من الغرب وأعمل في الشرق
I even [at] that time was not speaking Swahili.
حتى ذلك الوقت لم أكن أتقن اللغة السواحلية
And when they came, they looted everything.
وعندما قدوموا نهبوا كل شيء
You can't speak Lingala because Lingala was from Mobutu,
لاتستطيع تحدث اللينجالا لان اللينجالا كانت لموتوبو
and everyone speaking Lingala is soldier.
وكل انسان يتحدث اللينجالا جندي
And I was from the same area to him.
كنت من نفس المنطقة
All my friends said, we are leaving because we are a target.
كل أصدقائي قالوا بأنهم سيغادرون فهم أهداف محتملة
But I'm not going to the east, because I don't know Swahili.
لكنني لاأستطيع الذهاب للشرق فأنا لاأجيد السواحلية
I stay. If I go, I will be killed.
لذا بقيت لو ذهبت لقتلت
I can't go back to my area -- it's more than 1,000 kilometers [away].
لاأستطيع العودة لمنطقتي – إنها تبعد أكثر من 1000 كيلومتر
I stayed after they looted everything.
بقيت بعد أن نهبوا كل شيء
We have been doing research on botany,
كنا نقوم بأبحاث على النباتات
and we have a small herbarium of 4,500 sheets of plants.
وكان لدينا 4500 عشبة صغيرة من نباتات مختلفة.
We cut, we dry and we packed them,
قطعناها وجففناها وقمنا بحفظها ,
we mounted them on a folder.
وأحصياناها على المجلدات.
Purpose: so that we start them for agriculture,
كان الهدف منها أن يتسنى لنا بعد ذلك الاستفادة منها في الزراعه ,
for medicine, for whatever, and for science,
والآدوية , وأشياء أخرى – والعلوم ,
for the study of the flora and the change of the forest.
ولدراسة النبات وتغير الغابة .
That is people moving around, that's even Pygmies.
الجميع في حركة دائمة ,حتى الاقزام.
And this is a bright guy, hard-working person, and Pygmy.
هذا الفتى القزم اللامع والمجد.
I've been working with him about 10 years.
عملت معه مايقارب العشر سنوات .
And with soldiers, they went to the forest for poaching elephants.
كان يذهب مع الجنود للغابة لآصطياد الفيلة .
Because he's Pygmy, he knows how to track elephants in the forest.
ولانه قزم يعلم كيف يقوم بخداع الفيلة .
He has been attacked by a leopard and they abandon him in the forest.
كان قد هوجم من قبل دبابات الليوبارد وقاموا برميه في الغابة .
They came to told me, I have to save him.
طلبوا مني أن أقوم بأنقاذه .
And what I did, I gave him just antibiotics
وهذا مافعتله قمت بأعطائه مضاد حيوي
that we care for tuberculosis.
نعالج به مرض السل .
And fortunately, I saved his life.
و لحسن الحظ, أنقذته .
And that was the language of the war.
هذه كانت هي لغة الحرب .
Everywhere there has been constant extraction of mineral,
في كل مكان إستخرج مستمر للمعادن ,
killing animals, the logging timbers and so on.
وقتل الحيوانات ,وقطع الأشجار ,وهلم جر .
And what of important things --
ومن أهم الآشياء ,
I think all of you here have a cell phone.
أعتقد أن جميعكم يحمل هواتف نقالة .
That mineral has killed a lot:
هذا المعدن الذي قتل الكثيرين –
five millions of Congolese have gone because of this
خمسة ملايين من الكونغوليين قضوا بسبب
Colombo-Tantalite -- they call it Coltan --
الكولمبوا-تانتليت ,أو الذي يسمونه الكولتان .
that they use it to make cell phones
هذا المعدن الذي يستخدمونه لصناعة الهواتف النقالة
and it has been in that area, all over in Congo. Extraction,
والمتواجد في هذه المنطقه ,في جميع ارجاء الكونغو , استخرج,
and good, big business of the war.
وكان تجاره جيدة وكبيره في هذه الحرب .
And what I did for the first war, after we have lost everything,
وأول شي فعلته في هذه الحرب ,وبعد فقداننا كل شي ,
I have to save something, even myself, my life and life of the staff.
كان علي أن أنقذ شيء ما, نفسي وحياتي ,وحياة الطاقم .
I buried some of our new vehicle engines, I buried it to save it.
قمت بدفن بعض محركاتنا الجديده , دفنتها لكي أحافظ عليها .
And some of equipment went with them,
وبعض من المعدات التي ذهبت معهم
on the top of the canopy, to save it.
على متن المظلات ,لآنقاذها .
He's not collecting plants, he's going to save our equipment
هو لايقوم بجمع النباتات .لذلك هو سيقوم بالحفاظ على معداتنا
on the canopy.
على المظلات
And with the material that's left --
مع المعدات التي تركت--
because they wanted to destroy it, to burn it,
ولانهم أرادوا تدميرها , وأحراقها.
they didn't understand it, they didn't go to school --
لأنهم لايفهمون ماهي , لم يذهبوا الى المدارس .
I packed it.
قمت بحزمها .
And that is me, going to, hurrying to Uganda,
. وهذا أنا , هرعت لآوغندا ,
to try to save that 4,000 material,
في محاولة مني لأنقاذ هذه ال 4,000 مادة,
with people carrying them on the bikes, bicycles.
مع الاشخاص الذين قاموا بحملهم على الدراجات الهوائية .
And after that, we succeeded.
بعد كل شي نجحنا .
I housed that 4,000 material at the herbarium of Makerere University.
قمت بأيواء 4,000 مادة في معشبة جامعة ماكيريري.
And after the war, I have been able to bring it back home,
. بعد أنتهاء الحرب , كنت قادرا على نقلها وأعادتها للوطن
so that we continue our studies.
وبهذا أكملنا دراستنا .
The second war came while we didn't expect it.
نشبت الحرب الثانيه بوقت لم نكن نتوقعه .
With friends, we had been sitting and watching match football,
كنا نجلس مع بعض الاصدقاء ونتابع مباراة كرة القدم ,
and having some good music with WorldSpace radio,
ونستمع لبعض الموسيقى على إذاعة وورلد سبيس ,
when it started, I think.
عندما بدأت , على ماأذكر.
So, it was so bad.
لذلك , كانت سيئة .
We heard that now from the east again the war started,
نسمع الآن , من المنطقه الشرقية مرة أخرى حرب تبدأ ,
and it's going fast.
وتتقدم بسرعة .
This time I think Kabila will go in place of, as he did with Mobutu.
هذه المره أعتقدت أن كابيلا سوف يذهب الى مكان ما ,كما فعل مع موبوتو.
And the reserve was a target to the rebels.
و المحمية كانت مستهدفة بالنسبة للمتمردين .
Three different movements and two militia acting in the same area
ثلاث حركات مختفلة ومليشيتان , يتحركون في نفس المنطقة
and competing for natural resources.
ويتنافسون على الموارد الطبيعية .
And there was no way to work.
ولم يكن يوجد طريقة لعمل شيء.
They destroy everything.
دمروا كل شيء .
Poaching -- oh, no way.
أصطادوا –لا , مستحيل .
And that's the powerful men. We have to meet and to talk to them.
وهؤلاء الرجال الاقوياء –كان علينا مقابلتهم والتحدث إليهم .
What's the regulation of the reserve
ماهو نظام المحمية
and what is the regulation of the parks?
وماهو نظام الآماكن العامة ؟
And they can't do what they are doing.
وأنهم لايستطيعون القيام بما يريدون .
So we went to meet them.
لذلك ذهبنا لمقابلتهم .
That is Coltan extraction, gold mining.
هذا هو استخراج الكولتان , وتعدين الذهب .
So, we started talking with them,
من أجل هذا تحدثنا معهم ,
convincing them that we are in a protected area.
وقمنا بأقناعهم أننا في منطقة محمية .
There are regulations
يوجد لوائح
that it's prohibited to do logging, mining and poaching, specifically.
تمنع القيام بقطع الآشجار والتعدين والصيد غير المشروع ,على وجه التحديد .
But they said, "You guys,
ولكنهم ردوا قائلين " أنتم ,
you think that soldiers who are dying are not important,
هل تعتقدون أن الجنود الذين يموتون ليسوا بذات أهمية
and your animals you are protecting are most important.
وأن حيواناتكم الذين تحمونهم أهم أكثر أهمية ".
We don't think so.
أننا لانعتقد ذلك .
We have to do it, because to let our movement advance."
نحن نقوم بفعل ذلك حتى نجعل حركتنا أسهل ومتقدمة .
I say, "No way, you are not going to do it here."
قلت ,"مستحيل, لن تقوم بفعل ذلك هنا."
We started talking with them and I was negotiating.
بدأنا بالحديث معهم وقمت أنا بالتفاوض .
Tried to protect our equipment, tried to protect our staff
حاولت حماية معداتنا ,حماية الموظفين
and the villages of about 1,500 people.
والقرية التي بها مايقارب 1,500 شخص .
And we continued.
وقمنا بالمتابعة .
But I was doing that, negotiating with them.
كنت أقوم بذلك,وأتفاوض معهم ,
Sometimes we are having meeting
وفي بعض الآحيان كنا نقابلهم
and they are talking with Jean-Pierre Bemba,
و يتحدثون مع جين-بيري بيمبا ,
with Mbusa Nyamwisi, with Kabila, and I'm there.
ومع مبوسا نايموسي, ومع كابيلا, وأكون أنا متواجد .
Sometimes, they talk to my own language, that is, Lingala.
في بعض الآحيان يتحدثون بلغتي ,لينغالا .
I hear it and what strategy they are doing, what they are planning.
كنت أستمع وأعرف استراتجيتهم , وماذا يخططون .
Sometimes, they are having a helicopter
في بعض الآحيان كان لديهم طائرات مروحية
to supply them with ammunition and so on.
لتقوم بتزويدهم بالذخائر وغيرها .
They used me to carry that, and I was doing counting,
استخدموني لأقوم بحملها وكنت أقوم بحسابها ,
what comes from where, and where, and where.
ومن أين تأتي ومن أين ومن أين .
I had only this equipment -- my satellite phone, my computer
لم يكن لدي سوى هذا الجهاز – هاتفي المتصل بالآقمار الصناعية , جهاز الحاسوب
and a plastic solar panel -- that I hide it in the forest.
وصفيحة بلاستكيه تعمل على الطاقه الشمسية في الغابة .
And every time, daily, after we have meeting,
وفي كل مرة , يوميا , بعد انتهاء اللقاء ,
what compromise we have, whatever,
الحل الوسط الذي نصل له ,مهما كان,
I go, I write a short email, send it.
أذهب , وأكتب رسالة بريد الآكتروني قصيرة ,وأرسلها .
I don't know how many people I had on my address.
لاأعلم عدد الأشخاص الذين أملك عنواينهم في حسابي ,
I sent the message: what is going about the progress of the war
أرسل رسالة عن أخر تطورات الحرب
and what they are planning to do.
ومالذي يخططون لفعله .
They started suspecting that what we do on the morning,
بدأوا بالآشتباه بأن مانفعله في النهار,
and the afternoon, it's on the news, BBC, RFI.
والمساء هو مايعرض على أخبار بي بي سي ,ار اف اي .
(Laughter)
(يضحك)
Something might be going on.
شيء ما سيحدث .
And one day, we went for a meeting.
في يوم من الآيام , ذهبنا للمقابلة .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Sorry.
أسف.
One day, we went to meet the Chief Commander.
في يوم من الآيام ذهبت لمقابلة قائدهم الآعلى .
He had the same iridium cell phone like me.
كان يحمل هاتف الآريديوم النقال كالذي أحمله .
And he asked me, "Do you know how to use this?"
وسألني ,"هل تعرف كيف تستخدمه ؟"
I said, "I have never seen it.
قلت,"لم أرى شيء كهذا من قبل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I don't know."
لاأعلم."
And I had mine on my pocket.
وكنت أحمل جهازي في جيبي .
So, it was a chance that they trusted me a lot.
تلك كانت الفرصة التي جعلتهم يثقوا بي ثقة تامة ,
They didn't -- they was not looking on me.
ولكنهم لم يفعلوا , لم يكونوا ينظروا الي .
So I was scared.
لذلك كنت خائفا.
And when we finished the meeting, I went to return it in the forest.
وعندما انتهى اللقاء أعدته للغابة .
And I was sending news, doing whatever,
وقمت بأرسال الآخبار , فعلت كل شيء,
reporting daily to the U.N., to UNESCO, to our institution in New York,
مراسلة يومية لقوات حفظ السلام, لليونسكو . للمؤسستنا في نيويورك
what have been going.
وأخبارهم بكل ما يجري .
And for that, they have been having big pressure to leave, to free the area.
ولهذا السبب كان عليهم ضغط كبير للرحيل, وتحرير المنطقه .
Because there was no way --
. ولانه لايوجد طريقة أخرى—
whatever they do, it's known the same time.
مهما فعلوا , كان ذلك معروفا .
During the first two rebellions, they killed all animals in the zoo.
خلال الفترة الاولى من عمليتي التمرد , قاموا بقتل جميع الحيوانات في حديقة الحيوانات.
We have a zoo of 14 Okapis, and one of them was pregnant.
لدينا حديقة حيوانات تتألف من 14 زرافة الآوكابيز. واحده منهم كانت حامل .
And during the war, after a week of heavy war, fighting in the area,
وخلال الحرب . وبعد أسبوع قاسي من الحرب ,والقتال في المنطقة.
we succeeded: we had the first Okapi.
نجحنا— لدينا أول زرافة آوكابي.
This is the only trouser and shirt remind me of this.
كانوا هاذين البنطال والقميص الوحيدين , على ماأذكر .
This is not local population, this is rebels.
هؤلاء ليسوا السكان المحليين , هؤلاء ثوار .
They are now happy sending the news
أنهم الآن سعيدين بالآخبار المرسلة اليهم
that they have protected the Okapi with the war,
وأنه تم حماية الآوكابي خلال الحرب
because we sent the news that they are killing
لأننا قمنا بأرسال أخبار بأنهم يقتلون
and poaching everywhere.
ويصطادون بطرق غير شرعية في كل مكان .
After a week, we celebrated the birthday of that Okapi,
بعد أسبوع أحتفلنا بمولد ألاوكابي ,
they killed an elephant, just 50 meters to the area
قاموا بقتل فيل .على بعد 50 كيلومتر فقط من المنطقة
where the zoo, where Okapi was born.
حيث توجد حديقة الحيوانات , المكان الذي ولدت به الآوكابي .
And I was mad.
جن جنوني .
I oppose it -- that they are now going to dissect it,
عارضت ذلك وهم الآن يحللونه
until I do my report and then I see the Chief Commander.
حتى أنهي تقريري ثم سأقوم بلقاء القائد الآعلى ,
And I succeeded.
وبالفعل نجحت .
The elephant just decayed and they just got the tusks.
تهاوى الفيل و حصلوا هم على الآنياب .
What we are doing after that -- that was the situation of the war --
ما الذي نستطيع فعله بعد ذلك, هذه هي حال الحرب .
we have to rebuild.
كان علينا أعادة البناء .
I had some money. I was paid 150 dollars.
كان لدي بعض المال – لقد قمت بدفع 150 دولاراً .
I devoted half of it to rebuild the herbarium,
خصصت نصفها لآعادة بناء المعشبة ,
because we didn't have good infrastructure to start plants.
لآنه لم يكن لدينا بنى تحتية جيدة لنبدأ بالزراعة.
Wildlife Conservation Society more dealing with plants.
الحفاظ على الحياة البرية يعتمد بشكل أكبر على الزراعة .
I started this with 70 dollars,
بدأت هذا العمل ب 70 دولاراً
and start fundraising money to where I've been going.
وبدأت بجمع التبرعات المالية لكل مكان كنت أذهب أليه .
I had opportunity to go all over,
كانت لدي الفرصة للذهاب الى كل مكان
where herbarium for my African material is.
توجد به معشبة من أجل مادتي الآفريقية.
And they supported me a bit, and I built this.
لقد دعموني قليلا, وقمت ببناء هذه .
Now, it's doing work to train young Congolese.
الآن يعمل من أجل تدريب الشباب الكنغوليين .
And also, what one of the speciality we are doing,
وأيضا, من الآشياء الخاصة التي نقوم بها ,
my design is tracking the global warming effect on biodiversity,
هو مشروعي الذي يتتبع تأثير أرتفاع الحرارة على التنوع الإحيائي ,
and what the impacts of the Ituri Forest is playing to uptake carbon.
وماهو التأثير الذي يلعبه على غابة ايتوري لأمتصاص الكربون .
This is one of the studies we are doing on a 40-hectare plot,
هذه أحدى الدراسات التي نقوم بها على 40 هكتار من الاراضي ,
where we have tagged trees and lianas from one centimeters,
بنفس المكان الذي أوسمت فيه الآشجار والنباتات الحبيلة من سنتيمتر واحد
and we are tracking them.
وتابعنا الدراسة عليها .
We have now data of about 15 years,
والآن لدينا معلومات عن مايقارب 15 سنة ,
to see how that forest is contributing to the carbon reductions.
لمعرفة كيفية مساهمة هذه الغابة للتخفيض من إنبعاث الكربون
And that is -- I think it's difficult for me.
وهذا كل شيء – أعتقد أنه صعب علي ذلك.
This is a very embarrassing talk, I know.
هذا كلام محرج جدا , أعرف--
I don't know where to start, where to finish it.
--لاأعلم من أين أبدأ ,وأين أنتهي .
When I was thinking to come here,
عندما كنت قادم الى هنا
what best title I wanted to say to my talk, I didn't find this.
فكرت في ماهو العنوان الملائم ؟ لم أجد العنوان المناسب لمحاضرتي
But now I think that I would have titled it, "The Language of Guns."
لكن الان أعتقد بأني وجدته "لغة السلاح"
Where are you people?
أين أنتم أيها الناس ؟
Now we are talking about reconstitution, rebuild Africa.
أنا الان أتحدث عن اعادة الدستور .. عن اعادة بناء أفريقيا
But is gun industries a tool to rebuild, or is it a game?
لكن هل صناعة الاسلحة أداة من ادوات أعادة البناء ؟ أم هل هي لعبة ؟
I think we see the war like a game --
أعتقد بأنكم تعتقدون أن الحرب لعبة --
like soccer, football.
ككرة القدم
Everybody is happy, but see what it's doing,
حيث الجميع سعداء ، لكن انظروا ماذا يحدث
see what is going in Darfur.
انظروا الى مايحدث في دارفور
Now we say, oh, my God.
الان نحن نقول يا الهي
See what the wars in Rwanda.
انظروا الى مافعلته الحرب في راوندا
That's because of the language of guns.
هذا بسبب لغة السلاح
I don't think that someone may blame Google,
لا اعتقد بان أحدهم سيلوم جوجل
because it's doing the right things,
لانها تقوم بالعمل الصحيح
even if people like Al-Qaeda are using Google
حتى ان كان بعض الاشخاص كالقاعدة يستخدمونه
to connect between them.
للاتصال فيما بينهم
But it's serving millions for the best.
لكنه يخدم ملايين الاشخاص نحو الافضل
But what is doing with gun industries?
لكن ماذا سنفعل بصناعة الأسلحة؟
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Thank you, thank you.
كريس اندرسون: اشكرك
Just wait over there.
فقط انتظر هنا
It's an amazing story.
انها قصة مدهشة
I suspect a lot of people here have the same question I have.
اعتقد بأن الكثير من الاشخاص هنا لديهم نفس السؤال
How can we help you?
كيف بإمكاننا مساعدتك ؟
Corneille Ewango: That's really embarrassing questions.
انه لسؤال محرج حقاً.
I think that now I feel nervous.
اشعر حاليا بالتوتر
And I think, helping us, people are acting sometimes by ignorance.
واعتقد ، مساعدتنا، يتصرف الناس احيانا بجهل
I did it myself.
فعلت ذلك بنفسي
If I know when I was young,
لو علمت منذ صغري
that [by] killing an elephant, I'm destroying biodiversity,
أنه بقتلي للفيلة أساعد في تدمير التنوع الإحيائي
I would not have done it.
لما كنت فعلت ذلك
Many, many of you have seen the talents of Africans,
العديد منكم قد شاهد بعض المواهب الافريقية
but there are few who are going to school.
لكن قلة فقط من هذه المواهب استطاعت ارتياد المدارس
Many are dying because of all those kind of pandemics,
العديد منهم يموتون بسبب الاوبئة
HIV, malaria, poverty, not going to school.
الايدز ,الملاريا ,الفقر لايذهبون الى المدرسة
What you can assist us, it's by building capacities.
كيف تستطيعون مساعدتنا ؟ ببناء القدرات
How many have got opportunity like me
كم عدد الذين تسنح لهم الفرصة مثلي
to go to U.S., do a master's?
للذهاب للولايات المتحدة لانهاء رسالة الماجستير
And go -- now, I'm in the Netherlands to do a Ph.D.
الان انا في هولندا لأقدم رسالة الدكتوراه
But many of them are just here, because they don't have money.
.لكن العديد من أبناء جنسي هنا لأنهم لايملكون المال فقط
And they can't go even to university.
لايستطيعون الذهاب الى الجامعة
They can't even attain the bachelor's degree.
حتى انهم لايستطيعون الحصول على شهادة البكالوريوس
Building capacities for the young generation
بناء القدرات للجيل الصاعد
is going to make a better generation
قادر على بناء جيل أفضل
and a better future tomorrow for Africa.
ومستقبل أفضل لأفريقيا
CA: Thank you, thank you.
شكراً لك، شكراً لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)